Rabbi Ozer Glickman of ישיבה Yeshiva University died yesterday.
Would you say a few words?
Sure.
We will dedicate this learning to Rabbi Ozer Glickman of blessed memory
of ישיבה Yeshiva University who died tragically suddenly unexpectedly yesterday. He was
a tremendous inspiration to me and to many others
and may his memory be for a blessing. אמן. Amen.
Sorry to hear
that. Alright, we're on עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
and we're going to pick up at the bottom of דף סד
עמוד ב. Daf Samech Dalet Amud Bet.
I'm going to
backtrack, haha, no סג עמוד ב Samech Gimmel Amud Bet so that
we can learn סד. Samech Dalet. I am going to backtrack just
a little bit and be six and a half lines from the
bottom on סג עמוד ב. Samech Gimmel Amud Bet. We have a
few rabbis that are meeting to discuss issues between the ישראל, Yisrael,
גר תושב, Ger Toshav, and the עובד כוכבים, Oved Kochavim, continuing our
סוגיות Sugyot on how to handle יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, what is
okay and what is not okay. We're going to encounter three of
these gatherings with three different discussions, so we're just going to go
back to the beginning of that and pick up from there. So,
we're at יתיב רב נחמן ועולא ואבימי בר פפא Yativ Rav Nachman
v'Ulla v'Avimi bar Pappa ויתיב רבי חייא בר אמי
גביהו
v'yativ Rabbi Chiya
bar Ami gabeihu ויתיבי וקמיבעיא להו. v'yativei v'kami bayei lehu. So this
is going to be the intro to those like three sections right
now. There's always going to be this יתיב, Yativ, that they're sitting
together. Interestingly,
just as גמרא Gemara structure,
why do we say יתיב Yativ these and these and these people
and then יתיב Yativ again רבי חייא? Rabbi Chiya?
Right? Like if they're all sitting together. Usually the second יתיב Yativ
is somebody that comes to make a decision, but in this case
it's going to be the decisions or the rulings of רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. Okay, here's the question.
יתיב Yativ they have it as a past tense here, is that
correct?
They were sitting. Yes.
Their sitting and studying this topic. Okay, so now, שכרו לשבור ביין
נסך מהו? Secharo lishbor b'Yayin Nesech mahu? מי אמרינן Mi amrinan כיון
דרוצה בקיומו kevan d'rotze b'kiyumo אסור assur או דילמא odilma כל למעוטי
תיפלה שפיר דמי. kol lemayutei tifla shapir dami.
So what is our situation? We have a non-Jew hiring a Jew
to work with him on something relating to יין נסך, Yayin Nesech,
how do we translate here? Libation wine, right, non-Jewish wine.
Okay, so real עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah wine.
Real עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah wine. So the non-Jew is hiring a
Jewish worker to work with him in the יין נסך. Yayin Nesech.
על פניו, Al panav, this is now the Jew is going to
get benefit from the יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, right? And like what
is the הלכה? Halacha?
Because the issue is, and this is going to become whatever,
one
of these rabbinic discussions, okay. What the non-Jew is really hiring the
person to do is to break the barrels of the יין נסך.
Yayin Nesech. Okay, that's the job.
Good.
So what is the problem? The problem now is that the Jew
has an interest in maintaining the wholeness of these barrels of יין
נסך Yayin Nesech so that he can have a job breaking the
barrels,
right?
Okay, so do we say that since he has an interest in
preserving these barrels until he himself breaks them so that he can
get paid for breaking them, so is his payment, the wages that
he's going to get for that, are those forbidden? Or can we
reason that because by breaking them he's reducing the
תיפלה, tifla, what?
Close? Because he's doing something that will reduce this impropriety, reduce the
existence of
יין נסך yayin nesech and all his friends to discuss different situations,
so just to make it more holistic I'm backtracking four lines. Okay.
And Rav Nachman says ישבור ותבוא עליו ברכה, Yishbor vetavo alav beracha,
may let him break those barrels and be blessed and this is
where you ended last yesterday. לימא מסייע ליה, Leima mesaye lei, so
now we're going to bring a ברייתא Beraita that supports this opinion.
אין עודרים עם עובד כוכבים בכלאים. Ein odrim im oved kochavim bekilayim.
Okay.
So of course we're going to go somewhere completely different in order
to try to find support for this discussion and the support comes
from כלאים. Kilayim. We have we are not allowed to have כלאים,
Kilayim, but there's something very beautiful in that פסוק. Pasuk.
Video,
so we can do this more freely. Okay. So he says you're
not allowed to hoe, to like till the ground, i.e., to
be productive with the עובד כוכבים Oved Kochavim when it comes to
a שדה כלאים. Sedeh Kilayim. Top of ס״ד ע״א, Samech Daled Amud
Aleph, אבל עוקרים עמו כדי למיעוטי התפלה. Aval okrim imo kedei lemi'utei
hatiflah. But it is permitted to uproot.
Okay, so it's not that we can't work in a שדה כלאים
Sedeh Kilayim at all, we can't work to make it more productive
but we can work to uproot it.
But
it's it's still a question because what if I what if I
have a job to uproot the whatever weeds in the שדה כלאים,
Sedeh Kilayim, right? And the next day I come and then it's
all done, so now I lost the job. Right?
So okay, so let's go let's go back one second and explore
this field a little more. סברוה
הא מני רבי
עקיבא היא דאמר המקיים בכלאים לוקה. Sevaruha
ha meni Rabbi
Akiva hi de'amar hamekayem bekilayim loke.
Where do we get this from? This is accordance with in accordance
with Rabbi Akiva that somebody that is מקיים בכלאים. Mekayem bekilayim. Okay,
so מקיים Mekayem in the sense of somebody who maintains the כלאים
Kilayim also is לוקה, Loke, also is liable to get lashes because
he helps the he does things to help the כלאים Kilayim grow.
How does it how
is this like Rabbi Akiva? רגע רגע. Rega, rega. In
the
middle of a thing. דתניא המנכש והמחפה בכלאים לוקה. Detanya hamenakesh vehamachape
bekilayim loke. This is what we've taught, we're taught in the ברייתא
Beraita one who is מנכש, Menakesh, takes out the weeds that interfere
with the growth of the plants, or מחפה, Machape, covers up the
seeds of the כלאים Kilayim so that they can grow, is getting
lashes. So from there
Rabbi
Akiva teaches אף המקיים, Af hamekayem, anyone that helps the כלאים, Kilayim,
for example I'm not even touching the field itself, I'm just building
a fence around it. Okay, so I'm helping the כלאים Kilayim grow.
What did you ask me?
I want to show the פסוק. Pasuk. How is it like Rabbi
Akiva? I would say this isn't like Rabbi Akiva because Rabbi Akiva
says it's לוקה Loke and here this guy wants it to be
around. רגע. Rega.
Unless you want to say even Rabbi Akiva says that the המקיים
כלאים Hamekayem Kilayim can go according to this.
This is just
what they say,
this is how Rabbi Akiva teaches it, because Rabbi Akiva says המקיים.
Hamekayem.
And you're saying
I'm saying or you can say this is exactly not like Rabbi
Akiva because Rabbi Akiva says you're לוקה Loke and over here you
can, you know, here this is going to be around until you
get rid of it and and if you will want it to
stay around a little bit longer Rabbi Akiva would say you're לוקה
Loke but over here you're saying it's no problem as long as
you're...
רגע. Rega. So let's see if we'll come around this conversation and
have a completely different answer. We're kind of in the middle listening
on the side. Okay. The פסוק Pasuk I want to show you
what Rabbi Akiva is doing with the with the פסוק. Pasuk. Okay.
מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא? Mai ta'ama deRabbi Akiva? אמר קרא שדך לא
תזרע כלאים. Amar kra sadecha lo tizra kilayim. אין לי אלא זורע
מקיים מניין? Ein li ela zore'a, mekayem minayin? Michael, pretty much your
question. How do we get this? So the פסוק Pasuk said...
No, that's not my question. But okay. Okay.
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. I missed being here. Okay.
The פסוק pasuk says you shall not sow your field with the
כלאים, kila'im, with the mixed forbidden kinds of seeds. From there we
should understand that the only thing we're not allowed to do is
זורע. zorea. How do we get the מקיים? mekayem? Right? How do
we get the additional things that we're not allowed to do? מקיים
מנין? Mekayem minayin? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, לא כלאים. lo kila'im. So
now I'll show you how רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is reading this
פסוק. pasuk. This is in ויקרא Vayikra 19:19. י"ט, Yud-tet, verse 19.
את חוקותי תשמורו בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים שדך לא תזרע כלאים ובגד
כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך. Et chukotai tishmoru behemat'cha lo tarbia kila'im
sadecha lo tizra kila'im uveged kila'im shatnez lo yaaleh alecha. The question
is
where do we breathe here according to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So
again, it says theoretically it says בהמתך לא תרביע behemat'cha lo tarbia
I'm going to read it without breathing so that you can see
different commas where it can come here even though the trope already
decided. Exactly. But but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wants to read it
in a double way. So okay, theoretically it says בהמתך לא תרביע
כלאים, behemat'cha lo tarbia kila'im, right? Don't mix your animal. שדך לא
תזרע כלאים, Sadecha lo tizra kila'im, don't mix your field. ובגד כלאים
שעטנז לא יעלה עליך, Uveged kila'im shatnez lo yaaleh alecha, and don't
wear שעטנז. shatnez. We know by the way from שעטנז shatnez that
you're not supposed to wear it, but if you have it in
your house, then that's not wearing it. Okay. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
takes the כלאים kila'im from the animal and reads it with the
field, thereby having two כלאים. kila'im. So there he'll read it בהמתך
לא תרביע behemat'cha lo tarbia breathe כלאים
שדך לא, kila'im sadecha lo, לא תזרע כלאים. lo tizra kila'im.
So your field don't do anything with כלאים. kila'im. Michael, don't kill
me. בבקשה, Bevakasha, check it.
Let's not mix.
כלאים שדך לא kila'im sadecha lo
and also don't seed. So from there we learn that like don't
do anything.
One thing...
wait, so how's he reading it again? בהמתך לא תרביע, Behemat'cha lo
tarbia,
breathe, כלאים שדך לא. kila'im sadecha lo. What about תזרע כלאים? tizra
kila'im? You have
to?
No, then לא תזרע כלאים.
lo tizra kila'im. לא תזרע כלאים Lo tizra kila'im פשיטא, peshita, we
already have this. We're looking for an additional thing that tells us
why מקיים לוקה. mekayem lokeh. I want to say something about the
word כלאים, kila'im, which I really like. Has nothing to do with
this, I just like it.
A little bit has to do with it. Where is it from?
What does it literally mean? Like we think of it as two
mixed things of something. But כלא. keleh. What is כלא? keleh? Prison.
Prison.
So this is like, it's רב הירש Rav Hirsch saying, it's kinds
that imprison each other. By being together they don't allow each other
their full expression or their full growth. It's very nice.
Right? How is this not allowing their full growth by being together?
I mean, I think
because a hybrid...
yes, there's certain hybrids that work, that support each other, and there's
certain hybrids...
I'm not talking about a hybrid, I'm talking about weaving two things
together from already existing stuff.
You're so...
so like we...
it's a bit more philosophical, we spiritualize I think. Like שעטנז shatnez
is, right, wool and flax. Yes, cotton linen. Linen is flax. Yeah,
okay. I don't know what's flax. Okay. Wool and linen. So supposedly
wool is like an animal kingdom, right, and this is a plant.
So there are ways to mix these two kingdoms that work and
ways that don't work. The same with the בהמות. behemot. There's בהמות
behemot that mix in the הרבעה harba'ah and בהמות behemot that it's
not good to put together in the הרבעה. harba'ah. There's plants, I'm
not a plant expert, but there's plants that take and give nutrients
that are complementary and things that are not. Anyway, רב הירש Rav
Hirsch looks at it as that these are items that imprison each
other, and I like that explanation. Okay.
So ואילו למיעוטי תיפלה שרי. Ve'ilu lemiyutei tifla shari. Okay.
So
this is we're closing the section supporting of רב נחמן Rav Nachman
saying
it's forbidden to have the כלאים, kila'im, but nevertheless, if one wishes
to have the כלאים kila'im temporarily so that he can have a
job so that he can get paid to uproot them, then reducing
תיפלה, tifla, right, reducing the bad thing is permitted. Likewise, getting
paid for breaking barrels of יין נסך yayin nesech is okay. רגע,
Rega, גמרא Gemara rejects it. Michael, where are you?
I've been here the whole time.
לא! Lo!
Immediately. אמיני, Amini, רבנן Rabbanan היא. hi. Okay. Well, what, who's, who's
this according that thinks that this is permitted to לעקור, l'akor, right,
to uproot the כלאים, kilayim, it is in accordance with the opinion
of the רבנן, Rabbanan, and they permit to have the diverse kinds,
but
forbid, let me see, from having the wine because this is we're
going to now get הנאה hana'ah from יין נסך yayin nesech. by
having a job that deals with it. So we're not done yet
with רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אי רבנן, Ei Rabbanan, מאי איריא עקרין?
mai irya okrin?
So if this is according with the opinion of the רבנן, Rabbanan,
why does the תנא tanna specifically permits
the
עקירה, akirah, right? Why do we teach that עקירה akirah of the
field of the כלאים kilayim is permitted? אפילו
קיומי נמי שפיר דמי,
afilu kiyumei
nami shapir dami, even maintaining the diverse kinds is permitted, and this
is what I mentioned earlier with the שעטנז shatnez
that
we're
not allowed to wear it, but we can own it. הכא במאי
עסקינן? hacha bemai askinan? So now really what are we talking about?
We're talking about something completely different. Maybe the comparison was not to
the point. כגון דקעביד חנם. kegon dik'avid chinam. ורב יהודה VeRav Yehuda
היא דאמר ליתן להם מתנת חנם אסור. hi de'amar liten lahem matnat
chinam asur. So now maybe we're dealing with something different. We're dealing
with a situation, a case where the עקירה, akirah, the uprooting was
done without getting paid. And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says that giving
a free, right, a מתנת חנם, matnat chinam, a gift for nothing
to the non-Jew is forbidden. Okay.
So which would mean then you shouldn't be allowed to work with
them to uproot it, but nevertheless you're allowed to because you're getting
rid of something that's אסור. asur.
Yes. Which is, yeah.
Okay. מדברי רבי יהודה נשמע לרבי עקיבא. midivrei Rabbi Yehuda nishma leRabbi
Akiva. So from רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, from the opinion of רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we may understand what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said.
And this is like a mathematical thing, right? Negative times negative is
a positive. So to, we say, לכלות איסור מותר, lechalot issur muttar,
right? To take away something that is bad is okay. לאו
אמר רב יהודה אסור ליתן להם מתנת חנם, lava amar Rav Yehuda
asur liten lahem matnat chinam, אבל למיעוטי תפלה שפיר דמי. aval lemi'utei
tifla shapir dami. This is what we just said, right? Doesn't רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda say that it's not allowed to give them an
unpaid, like a מתנת חנם? matnat chinam?
But to reduce bad thing is permitted? This is a question.
לרבי עקיבא leRabbi Akiva נמי. nami.
This is the same like what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. אף על גב, af al gav,
אף
על גב דאמר רבי עקיבא המקיים בכלאים לוקה, af al gav de'amar
Rabbi Akiva amekayem bekilayim loke, למיעוטי תפלה שפיר דמי, lemi'utei tifla shapir
dami, ותו לא מידי. vetu lo midei. Thank God for Rabbinic discussions
that sometimes end. So even though רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said המקיים
amekayem is also not okay if you support the כלאים kilayim is
not okay, but taking away from something bad is good, ותו לא,
vetu lo, and nothing more is to be said on this matter.
It's so nice. It's in modern Hebrew also you have this expression
ותו לא, vetu lo, and no more.
All right, shall
we
do. Second, second situation where now we are sitting with the same,
the same רבנן, Rabbanan, they come back together. הדור יתבי וקמיבעיא להו.
hador yatvei vekamibayei lehu. דמי עבודת כוכבים ביד עובד כוכבים מהו.
dmei avodat kochavim
beyad oved kochavim mahu. Okay,
second situation.
Right,
so first situation was somebody Jewish getting paid to break the barrel
of the יין נסך. yayin nesech, Second one is what about the
money that the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim gets from עבודת כוכבים, avodat
kochavim, דמי עבודת כוכבים, dmei avodat kochavim, what about it? מי תופסת
דמי ביד עובד כוכבים או לא?
mi tofset dmei beyad oved kochavim o
lo? If I have, if I, I'm not a good example.
If the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim has an עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim
and he pays it and now he has money, he needs money
to go to the מכולת makolet to buy himself food for his
family. What about, what is the status of that money? And can
a ישראל Yisrael accept this kind of money? Right, so now עובד
כוכבים oved kochavim X sold his עבודה זרה, avoda zara, got money,
and comes to the Jew. Jew's store and wants to buy with
it. Can we do this?
Okay. אמר ליה Amar leh רב נחמן מסתברא Rav Nachman mistabra. looks
like שדמי עבודת כוכבים she'dmei avodat kochavim ביד עובד כוכבים beyad oved
kochavim מותר. mutar. והנהו דאתו לקמיה דרבה בר אבוה Ve'henhu de'atu lekamei
de'Rabba bar Avuha we're going to have a case.
אמר להו Amar lehu זילו זבינו כל מה דאית לכו וטו אתגיירו.
Zilu zevinu kol mah de'it lechu vetu itgayeru. You're going to fix
it.
Heard you called it.
Can I pause this?
Yeah. Of course.
Next seating of the rabbis.
We're going to the next seat and we're asking about a money
of עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim in the hands of the עובד כוכבים.
oved kochavim. Is that okay?
And רב נחמן Rav Nachman says we're like a third of the
way down on ס"ד א, Samech Dalet Aleph, מסתברא דמי עבודת כוכבים
ביד עובד כוכבים מותרים. mistabra dmei avodat kochavim beyad oved kochavim mutarin.
It seems like it's permitted. And we have a situation which we
just looked at, we're just reading right now, that people came in
front of a case, yeah, somebody non-Jewish came in front of רבה
בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha and he said, רבה בר אבוה Rabba
bar Avuha said to them, go sell everything you have and then
convert, i.e., get rid of the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
right? Get rid of your עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, make money for
it, and then convert so that you'll have the money from it,
i.e., you can use it. מאי טעמא? משום דקסבר דמי עבודת כוכבים
ביד עובד כוכבים מותרים. Mai ta'ama? Mishum de'kasavar dmei avodat kochavim beyad
oved kochavim mutarin. This is a question we're asking. Did he mean
this?
That you can sell your עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim and then the
money is okay? ודלמא שאני התם דכיון דדעתיה לאגיורי ודאי בטלה. Ve'dilma
shani hatam de'keivan de'da'ateih le'igyurei vadai batla.
Okay, so unclear if this is a ראיה, raya, if this is
a proof, because here we don't have an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
that sold the עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim just to use it for
anything, but they sold it in order to convert, right? So they
clearly like annulled the status of the עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim and
therefore were able to use it. So there's a difference between somebody
doing it for
a
ביטול, bitul, right? Because they don't want it anymore or not. אלא
מהא. Ela me'ha. So now we're going to try to bring a
proof from somewhere else. This was not a great proof, this story.
אלא מהא, ישראל שהיה נושה בעובד כוכבים מנה. Ela me'ha, Yisrael she'hayah
nosheh be'oved kochavim maneh. He was
a
creditor to a non-Jew for a hundred דינר denar ומכר עבודת כוכבים
והביא לו, יין נסך והביא לו, מותר. umachar avodat kochavim ve'hevi lo,
yayin nesech ve'hevi lo, mutar. אבל אם אמר לו המתן לי עד
שאמכור עבודת כוכבים ואביא לך, יין נסך ואביא לך, אסור. Aval im
amar lo hamten li ad she'emkor avodat kochavim ve'avi lecha, yayin nesech
ve'avi lecha, assur. So the situation is that if this happens, okay,
that the עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, the Jew was the creditor to
the non-Jew. The עובד כוכבים oved kochavim owes the Jew money. In
order to pay back the money, he sells the עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and brings it to him. If he does that with יין
נסך, yayin nesech, that is permitted. But if he says to the
Jew, wait wait wait, I have to go sell my idolatrous stuff
first and then I'll bring it to you or the יין נסך,
yayin nesekh then no.
Meaning, you don't need to inquire as
to the source of funds.
TMI, right? Too much information. Don't tell me where you're getting it
from.
But say he did, but he didn't say, you know, go wait.
He said oh okay.
Because then the issue is, like our issue was earlier, that then
the Jew has an interest in the preservation, how would you say,
of the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The Jew wants the עבודה זרה
avodah zarah to survive so that he's going to get paid. It's
better for him if he doesn't know what is the source of
that money. And the non-Jew has a business, whatever, he can be
anything, right? He can be a policeman, teacher, lawyer. Also he's selling
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. מה לעשות? Mah la'asot? Everybody makes his living
from something. But if it's the opposite, then the Jew is like
going to lose sleep over like oh my god, I hope nothing
happens to this עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? Because otherwise I'm not
going to get my money back. Okay. מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא
סיפא? אמר רב ששת, סיפא משום דהוה ליה כרוצה בקיומו. Mai shna
reisha u'mai shna seifa? Amar Rav Sheshet, seifa mishum de'hava leh ke'rotzeh
be'kiyumo. This is exactly what we've explained. What is the difference between
the beginning and the end? רב ששת Rav Sheshet says the end
is that the Jew desires the עבודה זרה avodah zarah to be
not
get destroyed, not get lost, not anything. Okay, וכי רוצה בקיומו כהאי
גוונא מי אסיר? Vekhei rotzeh bekiumo kehai gavna mi asir?
So is the money now forbidden in such a situation? והתנן, Vehatnan,
let's bring another situation. גר ועובד כוכבים שירשו אביהן עובד כוכבים. Ger
veoved kochavim sheyarshu avihen oved kochavim. This is an interesting situation which
I
have to tell you I love the גמרא Gemara for it, because
somehow we think that once upon a time people lived differently and
they had different families and all that. And lo and behold, here
we have a situation where there's two brothers. One is a convert
and one is an idol worshiper, and they are going to inherit
goods from their father.
This happened to me.
Well, I
let's just say these situations happened, and apparently happened two thousand years
ago. It's like, it's super cool. Okay. גר יכול לומר לו טול
אתה עבודה זרה ואני מעות טול אתה יין נסך ואני פירות.
Ger yakhol lomar lo tol ata avodah zarah vaani maot tol ata
yayin
nesekh vaani perot. אם משבאו לרשות הגר אסור. Im mishebau lerashut hager
asur. So possibility to say, let's split it up. You take
the idolatrous stuff,
I'll take the big inheritance. You take the wine, I'll take the
fruit. But if the—if the גר ger is going to get it,
then it's forbidden. This is also problematic because now the גר, ger,
who is now really already Jewish, has an interest, right? Like he
relies to get his inheritance based on his brother getting—taking the עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, רגע, rega, up it a little bit. אמר
רב בר עולא מתניתין בעבודה זרה המתחלקת לפי שבריה. Amar Rav Bar
Ula matnitin baavodah zarah hamit-haleket lefi shevareha.
This—this ruling is also about idolatrous stuff that can be divided by
its shards, by the שברים, shevarim, by the pieces. For example, if
the idolatry is made out of gold, right? Then each one of
the pieces is going to be good.
Okay, so great. But what in the matter of wine, right?
תינח עבודה זרה יין נסך מאי איכא למימר? Tinakh avodah zarah yayin
nesekh mai ika lemeimar? Where do we find a situation—this is a
quiz—where do we find before you go, this is a situation, where
do we find יין נסך yayin nesekh useful in שברים, shevarim,
when things are broken?
We had that earlier a long time ago.
We did have it earlier. I had the honor and the pleasure
to
teach the special whatever it was called.
Yes, exactly.
Yes, yes, yes. So we—we had a—that the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
have a thing called חרס אדריאני. Cheres Adriani. There was a משנה
Mishnah very early on in this מסכת masechet that we were talking
about the idea of חרס אדריאני, Cheres Adriani, which was a clay
that was not completely baked. That's for the יין נסך yayin nesech,
though.
That's more the jug. It was
soaked in—it was soaked—this is what made the חרס אדריאני. Cheres Adriani.
It was soaked in wine. You could carry the broken pieces of
the חרס, cheres, soak it in water, it would be like a
concentrate, yeah, Kool-Aid concentrate, kind of thing. And then you can make
out of—out of it a drink. Okay, רגע. rega. So that means
that
first
we were asking, okay, maybe the גר ger wants the preservation of
the idolatrous stuff. Here is somewhere where—he could say, oh, I don't
care if it breaks, right? I don't care if the inheritance breaks,
dot dot dot. But he'll still—he'll still get it, right? He'll—he'll get
benefit from it.
והלא רוצה בקיומו שלא יגנבו ושלא יאבדו אלא אמר רב פפא ירושת
הגר קאמר שאני ירושת הגר דאקילו בה רבנן גזירה שמא יחזור לקלקולו.
Vehala rotzeh bekiumo shelo yignevu veshelo yavedu ela amar Rav Papa yerushat
hager kaamar shani yerushat hager deakilu bah rabanan gezeirah shema yakhzor lekilkulo.
Okay. So
he still wants the ירושה, yerushah, right? He still wants his inheritance
to
be preserved somehow. What if it's stolen or lost? He'll be worried.
So we—we like we prove that he cares about the idolatrous stuff.
But רב פפא Rav Papa says
the—you say that there's like a difficulty in the case of the—of
the convert, of the גר. ger. This is a different situation which
we may not be able to exactly learn from one to another
because the sages, רבנן, rabanan, they—they had a little bit of a
קולא kula with it. They were lenient with the גר. ger.
Lest he's going to go back to being corrupted. So let's
understand
this. רגע. rega.
Okay,
so the convert can still get his inheritance, but in the case
of somebody who's not a convert and desires to maintain the object
of an idol worship, then it's forbidden for him to get any
property, any benefit from it, any profit from it. תניא. Tanya. All
right, top of ס״ד עמוד
ב. Samach-Daled
Amud-Bet.
תניא נמי הכי במדברים אמורים שיורשו אבל נשתתפו אסור. Tanya nami hachi
bamedebarim amurim sheyerashu aval nishtatefu assur. This is also taught in a
ברייתא Baraita that what is the case, what case is this statement
that the convert and the gentile can share property, it's only in
the case that they are ירשו, yerashu, that they inherit. But if
they were partners, it's forbidden. Okay, so we came to the end
of this. So
yes,
I can be a partner in business with a non-Jew, but not
if it involves עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, yeah. Not if it involves benefiting
from the עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. This is what it seems from
here. And
we're
not learning הלכה, halacha, we're learning גמרא. Gemara. So this might get,
you know, further on unpacked in the next 1800 years, right, in
different ways. There's also,
especially in the next one, is that
we've already had previous conversations about, right, some like the חרס אדריאני,
Cheres Adriani, whatever, like different issues of how the Jew and the
non-Jew divide stuff and now we'll see we're bringing back גר תושב
Ger Toshav and what is his role in this. And the ראשונים
Rishonim and אחרונים Achronim debate these issues further. So it doesn't mean
that I don't want to say, I'm not saying yes or no,
but it just doesn't mean that where we end up here, this
is where everybody is going to hold for the next 2000 years.
But at least this discussion gives leniency
to
the גר ger convert vis-a-vis stuff that he might inherit but not
in a case where there is a partnership. There's also issues of
like the convert is he like a newborn, right? He's a new
person. And why are we all of a sudden worried about the
inheritance? And there's some leniencies there. Okay. Third case. Top of ס״ד,
Samach-Daled, second line.
Back there sitting, הדורי יתבו וקמיבעי להו. Hadori yatvu vekamibei lehu.
So now this is our third case. גר תושב מהו שיבטל עבודת
כוכבים? Ger Toshav mahu sheyevatel Avodat Kochavim?
Can a גר תושב, Ger Toshav, is our question, can a גר
תושב Ger Toshav annul the status of an עבודת כוכבים? Avodat Kochavim?
רב
נחמן Rav Nachman who is the opinion here. רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says דפלח מבטל דלא פלח לא מבטל. Dephalach mevatel delo phalach lo
mevatel.
So we have an
opinion,
we had an earlier discussion between ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says number one, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
that ישראל Yisrael can never annul an עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. We
had that conversation when we talked about, it was also lucky to
be here for that, when we talked about a Jew finding an
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and the fear of him picking it up,
causing a קנין kinyan and then never being able to cancel that
status, go to ים המלח Yam HaMelach and that whole journey. Okay,
but what about the גר תושב? Ger Toshav? The גר תושב Ger
Toshav is a category in between, right? We have the עובד כוכבים
Oved Kochavim for sure we know what is his status, and the
ישראל Yisrael we know what is his status. What is the גר
תושב? Ger Toshav? Can he? And we have a principle: if somebody
worships an עבודת כוכבים, Avodat Kochavim, he can also annul. דפלח מבטל
דלא פלח לא מבטל. Dephalach mevatel delo phalach lo mevatel. If he
doesn't worship, if he doesn't have a relationship with this עבודה זרה,
Avoda Zara, he can't. או דילמא כל דמיניה מבטל והאי בר מיניה
הוא. O dilma kol dminei mevatel vehai bar minei hu.
So is this the case that somebody can revoke the status when
it's not his? Or it should be reasoned that anyone who is
the same kind of idol worship, then he can revoke the status
and a גר תושב Ger Toshav is... is he of the same
kind of idol worshipers? What is the status of the גר תושב
Ger Toshav vis-a-vis this? Again,
we see רב נחמן. Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman. מסתברא. mistabra
רב נחמן Rav Nachman holds that opinion and brings it here again.
דפלח מבטל. Dephalach mevatel. Somebody who is the worshipper itself, himself, herself,
can revoke the status but somebody who is not cannot. Huh? We
had this. Yeah. מיתיבי. Meitivei. Challenge. ישראל שמצא עבודת כוכבים בשוק, Yisrael
shematza avodat kochavim bashuk, עד שלא באת לידו, ad shelo bat liyado,
אומר לו עובד כוכבים ומבטלה. omer lo oved kochavim umvatla. Okay.
So in the case of a Jew who found an object of
idolatry in the שוק, shuk, in the marketplace,
as long as he doesn't—it's not like come into his possession, right,
until לא באת לידו, lo bat liyado, he says to the idolater,
and the idolater can revoke the status. מי שבאת לידו, Mi shebat
liyado, אינו אומר לעובד כוכבים ומבטלה, eino omer l'oved kochavim umvatla, מפני
שאמרו, mipnei she'amru, עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חברו, oved
kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo veshel chaveiro, בין עובדה ובין שאינו עובדה.
bein ovdah uvein she'eino ovdah. Okay. So once the Jew owns this,
now it's his, the non-Jew cannot cancel the status of the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah that's owned by the Jew because we've said, the
עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חברו. oved kochavim mevatel avodat
kochavim shelo veshel chaveiro. He only can cancel
the idolatrous status of the idolatry of himself and of חברו. chaveiro.
We don't know yet what חברו chaveiro is and we might have
a couple of explanations, so we'll have a digression one, digression two.
בין עובדה ובין שאינו עובדה, Bein ovdah uvein she'eino ovdah, whether he
worships it and whether he doesn't worship it. Yes.
This kind of implies it doesn't even refer that he owned it.
Yes, but I think we had this discussion earlier, that if a—if
a ישראל Yisrael
finds an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, he can say to a עובד
עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, not necessarily עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah
zarah of this עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, cancel the status, and then
he can pick it up and it's like nothing anymore and all
that.
It's a little bit hard to understand, I think. For us it's
a little bit hard to understand and I
was
talking to somebody over שבת Shabbos that it's like there's an idea
that we have different temptations in our society and the temptation of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah the way it was back then, we don't
have in the same weight, you know, in the same כובד. koved.
So we have a little bit of a hard time understanding what
does it mean that whatever, here there's a little, I don't know,
Shiva statue, right, that was made for idolatry and now I'm going
to pick it up and I'm going to get zapped basically, right?
That's like a spiritual... so we don't exactly know what to do
with it in עבודה זרה avodah zarah terminology.
My—not metaphor, not the right משל mashal though for it is like,
okay, if this was something radioactive, right? If this was something that
was harmful and there was something about it that was harmful. It's
not visible. I can be like, oh, let me go pick it
up, right? And I have somebody else that can come and
de—de-do this, right?
Whatever, it's a suitcase that is a bomb, right? Somebody can... how
do you call it?
Disarm it? Or whatever, right? Somebody can make it back into a
regular suitcase that's not a bomb. Then I can pick it up
and walk away with it or throw it in the trash or
with whatever. But as long as it has this, I don't know
if it's helpful, but this is my—my metaphors for myself so that
I can make sense out of it. Okay. So let's go first
to the last piece. What does it mean בין עובדה ובין שאינו
עובדה? bein ovdah uvein she'eino ovdah? This is what we just talked
about
right now. מאי עובדה ומאי שאינו עובדה? Mai ovdah u'mai she'eino ovdah?
אילימא אידי ואידי עובד כוכבים, Ileima idi ve'idi oved kochavim, היינו שלו
ושל חברו. hainu shelo veshel chaveiro. אלא לאו עובדה עובד כוכבים, Ella
lav ovdah oved kochavim, ומאי שאינו עובדה גר תושב? u'mai she'eino ovdah
Ger Toshav? ושמע מינה גר תושב נמי מבטל. Ushma mina Ger Toshav
nami mevatel. Okay. What—what did we just say?
The ברייתא Baraisa says עובד כוכבים oved kochavim can cancel the עבודת
כוכבים avodat kochavim his or his friend, whether he worships it or
whether he doesn't worship it. What does it mean?
If we say that this and this are referring to the non-Jew,
that's like that statement in the ברייתא Baraisa we were just looking
at.
So he can revoke the status of this idolatry or something
that—that's his, עובדה, ovdah, or שאינו עובדה, she'eino ovdah, or something that
belongs to another person.
But maybe there's another way to understand it. Worships it belongs to
the עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, right, to the Gentile. שאינו עובדה She'eino
ovdah maybe means the גר תושב. Ger Toshav. Okay, so when we
say... עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים, Oved Kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim, back
in the ברייתא, Baraita, עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חברו
בין עובדה ובין שלא עובדה, Oved Kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo veshel
chaveiro bein ovda uvein shelo ovda, namely maybe that means that the
גר תושב Ger Toshav can cancel an עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim, and
yes, an idolatrous object, maybe. Immediately the גמרא Gemara says
לא, Lo,
לעולם אימא לך אידי ואידי עובד כוכבים. Le'olam eima lach idi ve'idi
Oved Kochavim. No, it's not possible that this is the גר תושב,
Ger Toshav, עובדה ולא עובדה ovda velo ovda is עובד כוכבים Oved
Kochavim and גר תושב, Ger Toshav, yes.
So in most cases it doesn't matter, but Steinsaltz simply has
גוי.
Goy. Yes, so I want to stay away from גוי Goy and
stay with the עובד כוכבים. Oved Kochavim.
And I know, I mean like Rabbi Lamm had these discussions here
too, that like is this politically correct or is it that our
גמרות Gemaras are updated to be politically correct and use עובד כוכבים
Oved Kochavim where originally it was גוי? Goy? Is there an original
to the original?
Like why? Leave me with my עובד כוכבים Oved Kochavim and don't
get into like this whole thing of where we are and who
we live with and are they this or are they that. I
want to learn it as גמרא Gemara and not make it, no,
I want to dance a little bit. Sometimes it's very current for
me and sometimes I'm like, hey, I don't know, this is what
they talked about, let's just live with it.
Okay. So, no, we can't mix the גר תושב Ger Toshav into
this paragraph we just had. לעולם אימא לך אידי ואידי עובד כוכבים.
Le'olam eima lach idi ve'idi Oved Kochavim. It must be that the
עובדה ושאינו עובדה ovda vesheino ovda must both mean to the עובד
כוכבים. Oved Kochavim. ודקאמרת היינו שלו ושל חברו. Udekamart, hainu shelo veshel
chaveiro. רישא, Reisha, זה וזה לפעור, zeh vezeh lePe'or, זה וזה למרקוליס.
zeh vezeh leMarkulis. סיפא, Seifa, זה לפעור וזה למרקוליס. zeh lePe'or vezeh
leMarkulis. פעור. Pe'or. So, it's
either we talk about עובד כוכבים Oved Kochavim that they all worship
the same thing, פעור Pe'or and this and this מרקוליס, Markulis, or
we can say עובדה ושאינו עובדה ovda vesheino ovda is like whatever,
I found a statue of פעור Pe'or and really I worship מרקוליס,
Markulis, I can still cancel. Back, we haven't finished the discussion about
the גר תושב. Ger Toshav. Who is the גר תושב Ger Toshav
and who is the גר תושב Ger Toshav in regards to this
question whether he can annul עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim based on the
principle, right, we have a principle that if you worship you can
and if you don't worship you can't.
So we have to define the גר תושב Ger Toshav to find
out if he's a worshiper in order for us to know if
he can cancel. Okay.
מתיבי: Metivei: איזהו גר תושב? Eizu Ger Toshav? כל שקיבל עליו בפני
שלושה חברים שלא לעבוד עבודת כוכבים דברי רבי מאיר. Kol shekibel alav
bifnei shelosha chaverim shelo la'avod avodat kochavim, divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir defines a גר תושב Ger Toshav as someone who accepted
upon himself in front of three חברים, chaverim,
undefined, but let's say that these are people that are devoted to
the observance of מצוות, mitzvot, alright, we had this in other
places too,
in other places it's about the tithing and
the טומאה tumah and other things. Right. So and he committed to
not be involved in idol worship. That's the opinion of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir of what is the definition of the גר תושב, Ger
Toshav, somebody who basically went in front of a בית דין, beis
din, right, in front of שלושה חברים shelosha chaverim and committed to
do this. וחכמים אומרים: Vachachamim omrim: כל שקיבל עליו שבע מצוות שקיבלו
עליהם בני נח. Kol shekibel alav sheva mitzvot shekiblu aleihem bnei Noach.
חכמים Chachamim say, no, it's somebody that accepted שבע מצוות בני נח,
sheva mitzvot bnei Noach, to which we are going to have to
immediately ask, well then we should have called him a בן נח.
ben Noach. What is the added value by calling him a גר
תושב? Ger Toshav? Must be more than the שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvot.
אחרים אומרים: Acheirim omrim: אלו לא באו לכלל גר תושב. Elu lo
ba'u lichlal Ger Toshav. No,
this is not a גר תושב Ger Toshav category, the בני נח.
bnei Noach. גר תושב Ger Toshav does more. אלא איזהו גר תושב?
Ela eizehu Ger Toshav? זה גר אוכל נבלות שקיבל עליו לקיים כל
מצוות האמורות בתורה חוץ מאיסור נבלות. Zeh ger ochel nevelot shekibel alav
lekayem kol mitzvot ha'amurot baTorah chutz mi'issur nevelot. So who is the
גר תושב? Ger Toshav? First of all is somebody that is not
by definition is somebody not transient because he's תושב. Toshav. He's יושב,
yoshev, right, he lives with us.
He is somebody who lives with us who's doing more than שבע
מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei Noach,
and he's look it says שקיבל עליו לקיים כל מצוות האמורות בתורה
חוץ מאיסור נבלות, shekibel alav lekayem kol mitzvot ha'amurot baTorah chutz mi'issur
nevelot, only one little thing that he's different, what is it? He
is eating נבלות, nevelot, not kosherly slaughtered animals.
Yes; but for a non-Jew to observe שבת, Shabbat, we learn elsewhere,
is a death penalty!
רגע, Rega, we're not done. We're in the middle of an exciting
conversation
and—רגע. rega. Okay.
But here we know something. מייחדים אצלו יין ואין מפקידים אצלו יין.
Miyachadim etzlo yayin v'ein mafkidim etzlo yayin. So we're continuing to define
the גר תושב, Ger Toshav, right? So right now our definition is:
his uniqueness is let's say he accepted upon himself the negative commandments,
but
he
eats נבילות. neveilot. Okay. He doesn't eat kosherly slaughtered animals, he eats
carcasses. Also: מייחדים אצלו יין ואין מפקידים אצלו יין. Miyachadim etzlo yayin
v'ein mafkidim etzlo yayin. What is the difference between מייחדים miyachadim and
מפקידים? mafkidim? We can leave wine with him for a short time
without supervision, but not for a long time. ואפילו בעיר שרובה ישראל,
Ve'afilu be'ir sheruba Yisrael, even in a city that has a majority
of Jews. אבל מייחדים אצלו יין ואפילו בעיר שרובה עובדי כוכבים.
Aval miyachadim etzlo yayin
ve'afilu be'ir sheruba ovdei kochavim. I'm gonna leave this שמנו, Shamno, okay,
you know, just a second.
Okay, so we leave wine with him for a short period of
time, whether it's a city that's mostly Jewish or a city that's
not mostly Jewish. Why don't we keep it for him with him
in a הפקדה hafkada for a long time? We just said he's
keeping all the מצוות. mitzvot. Why don't we keep the wine with
him in a הפקדה hafkada for a long time?
We're—okay, we're like we trust him, but we also worry that something
might happen. So we don't think he's gonna mix it with יין
נסך, yayin nesech but we think that maybe he'll mix it with
his own wine, or switch it, and with his own wine he's
not as careful. So back to that example, you know, whatever of
the radioactive thing, how far do we want to keep our hand
from it? Okay.
שמנו כיינו, Shamno keyeino, we say. His oil is treated like his
wine in terms of what we're—what we're allowed to do, right? So
we can have הנאה, hana'ah, but we are forbidden for שתייה. shtiyah.
We're forbidden to drink it. גמרא Gemara immediately challenges this sidebar. Remember,
we're talking about the גר תושב. Ger Toshav. We're not done with
him. I'll try to do it in the three minutes left there.
I know I have five, but I also know we all have
a long day here. Okay. שמן מי קא הוי יין נסך? Shemen
mi ka havi yayin nesech? אלא יינו כשמנו. Ela yeino keshamno. Should
be backwards, not the oil like the wine, but the wine like
the oil. We assume that his wine is allowed in הנאה ואסור
בשתייה. hana'ah ve'asur bishtiyah. And the same—the שמן, shemen,
they're mutual. ולשאר כל דבר הרי הוא כעובד כוכבים. Velish'ar kol davar
harey hu ke'oved kochavim. All the other items, he's like an עובד
כוכבים. oved kochavim. רגע, מחלוקת. Rega, machloket. רבן שמעון אומר: יינו יין
נסך. Rabban Shimon omer: yeino yayin nesech. רבן שמעון Rabban Shimon actually
says that the wine of the גר תושב, Ger Toshav, because he's
not so so scrupulous, we might as well think of it as
יין נסך and just like not go there. It's too close, right?
It's whatever. Eating in a vegan place. It might be good, but
who knows what's in it? Maybe they didn't check the lettuce. Don't
go there. ואמרי לה: מותר בשתייה. Ve'amrei lei: mutar bishtiyah. And then
there's also the completely opposite opinion, which we have as a vegan
restaurant, that says: Yeah, what could possibly go wrong? We trust the
guy, he's fulfilling all the מצוות, mitzvot, he went in front of
this בית דין, beis din, we permit it. Okay, back. Asking. קתני
מיהא ולשאר כל דבריו הרי הוא כעובד כוכבים. Katani miha velish'ar kol
devarav harey hu ke'oved kochavim. We just made the statement, the ברייתא
baraita just made the statement that says: For everything else he's like
עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. What is everything else?
Where is he like an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim and where is
he like a Jew? What—what are you trying to say? למאי הלכתא?
Lemai hilchata? לאו דמבטל עבודת כוכבים כעובד כוכבים? Lav de'mevatel avodat kochavim
ke'oved kochavim? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: לא, ליתן רשות ולבטל רשות.
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: lo, litten reshut u'levatel reshut.
So,
with regards to what הלכה? halacha?
Can—now back, can he be מבטל, mevatel, can he annul the status
of an idolatrous object just like any other עובד כוכבים? oved kochavim?
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak says, no.
The only place where he's like an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim is
ליתן רשות ולבטל רשות. litten reshut u'levatel reshut. Anyone wants to guess
where we are?
רשות Reshut has to do with שבת Shabbos and with creating an
עירוב eruv on שבת. Shabbos. In order to create an עירוב, eruv,
you need a... Basically it's a תקנה takanah so that the Jews
live together. You need to be, right, my house is my private
domain, yours is, what if we have a common yard? We have
to create an עירוב eruv in order for us to be able
to carry, right, and to extend the private domain into the, into
the רשות. reshut.
We don't let the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim be part of this,
we also don't let the גר תושב ger toshav to be part
of it. ודתניא, V'detanya, this is taught in the ברייתא, beraita, ישראל
מומר משמר שבתו בשוק מבטל רשות. Yisrael mumar meshameir shabbato bashuk mevatel
reshut. ישראל Yisrael
who is an apostate, מומר, mumar, he observes Shabbat outside,
right,
in בפרהסיא, befarhesya, in public,
he can, like, give up... okay, this is a little bit complicated,
but like, he can give up his right to his domain in
order to be part of this thing, so that the Jews can
have their רשות הפרט, reshut haprat, so that they can do their
עירוב. eruv. This doesn't mean that you don't own your place, but
you can give up your right to that particular domain for the
sake of Shabbos. שאינו משמר שבתו בשוק אין מבטל רשות. She'eino meshameir
shabbato bashuk ein mevatel reshut. If he does not observe Shabbat even
in public places, then he cannot
renounce this domain business. מפני שאמרו ישראל נותן רשות ומבטל רשות. Mipnei
she'amru Yisrael noten reshut umevatel reshut. Only the Jew can give the
rights away for his place in order to create an עירוב. eruv.
It's really a rabbinic תקנה takanah for the Jews to be living
together. ובעובד כוכבים עד שישכור. Uve'oved kochavim ad sheyiskor. כיצד? Keitzad? אומר
לו רשותי קנויה לך רשותי מבוטלת לך קנה ואין צריך לשכור. Omer
lo reshuti knuya lach reshuti mevutelet lach kana ve'ein tzarich liskor. But
with regards to the non-Jew,
this is not effective, he can't do this as an owner, only
unless the non-Jew leases his domain in the courtyard to the Jew.
How so? He may say to another Jew, this I give you
my, I give the rights to my domain or the rights to
these domains are now renounced. This is, obviously can't do it in
Shabbos itself,
but can do it for the purpose of creating of an עירוב
eruv only among the Jews. For the purpose of this, the גר
תושב ger toshav is considered an עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. For the
purpose of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, he's not considered an עובד כוכבים.
oved kochavim. Therefore he cannot cancel. He follows back into the rule
of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, if you worship it, you can cancel
it, if you don't worship it, you can't cancel it. He doesn't
worship it, he can't cancel it. Thank you very much, we'll pick
up from רב יהודה Rav Yehuda at the bottom of ס"ד עמוד
ב' Samech Dalet amud bet tomorrow.
Everybody have a fabulous day.
Live from New York.